

ASTROPHYSICS RESEARCHER . GALAXY FORMATION & EVOLUTION

🛮 🖰 (+1) 647-221-0865 | 🔀 juanpabloalfonzo@protonmail.com | 🏕 juanpabloalfonzo.github.io | 🖸 juanpabloalfonzo | 🛅 juan-pablo-alfonzo-7b9623201

Summary_

My research lies in the area of **galaxy evolution and formation** within astrophysics. My research area in particular is very programming/computationally heavy. I like describing my area of research as an **intersection between astronomy and computer science**, specifically **machine learning and data science**. A lot of the work I have done and hope to continue doing heavily involves programming and using Python based algorithms. These algorithms have a heavy emphasis on machine learning and **artificial neural networks** to help answer research questions associated with galaxy evolution and formation. Along with this, my current research is expanding to also involve **programming theoretical physics models into a computational simulation** to test them against observed data.

Research Experience _____

University of Toronto

Toronto, Canada

SURP RESEARCHER/ RESEARCH ASSISTANT

May 2021 - Present

- Working on training a convolutional neural network (CNN) to classify galaxies in the MaNGA survey, while studying what features of the galaxies the neural network is focusing on to make the classification with the use of CAM methods.
- Network being created and trained using the **pytorch** Python package and working in a **Linux based environment** and using **Google Colab**
- Final goal is to have the CNN be able to predict the star forming history of the galaxies from their visual image and spectral information. Aim to not only having a working CNN but to be able to pick it apart to understand how it is making decisions and extract relevant physics
- Project Supervisor: Dr. Kathreik Iyer (Dunlap Institute)

University of Toronto Toronto, Canada

Undergraduate Researcher

Aug. 2020 - Apr. 2021

- · Investigated morphological changes in galaxies as they evolve in time, by studying their internal kinematics using the MaNGA survey.
- Analysis being done using Python based code with heavy use of machine learning algorithms such as DB scan and PCA from the sci-kit learn library. Full write up of project can be found here
- Unique use of PCA which focused more on using the actual PC vectors rather than using them as the basis in a PC profile plot
- Project Supervisor: Dr. Mubdi Rahman (Dunlap Institute)

Work Experience _____

Tutor Doctor/Independent

Toronto, Canada

MATH & PHYSICS TUTOR

May 2018 - Present

- Tutored various high school students in **senior level math and physics courses**
- Improved my communication/collaborative skills in order to ensure I was communicating the content as clearly as possible to my students

CHARITY FUNDRAISER, TEAM LEADER POSITION

Toronto, Canada Apr. 2019 - Sept. 2019

- · Canvassed various neighborhoods in order to collect monthly donations for non-profits such as: Sistering, World Vision, and Save the Children
- Lead teams of fundraisers (8-15 people), was in charge of organizing which streets they went to, tracking their progress and making sure everything was running smoothly
- Improved my leadership skills as I was in a position where I coached fellow fundraisers. Lead team huddles to energize the team and ensure our day was as successful as possible
- Enriched my public speaking skills and learned how to present complicated topics in a concise and engaging manner

Presentations and Talks

SURP Poster Fair

Donorworx

Toronto, Canada

SCIENCE POSTER PRESENTATION

Aug. 13 2021

- Presented poster that summarized summer research in fair were all members of the astronomy department at the University of Toronto were invited to attend. Won top poster award
- Project poster can be seen by clicking here

SDSS Collaboration Meeting 2021

Baltimore, USA

PRESENTER IN DATA 1 SERIES AND LIGHTING TALK 1 SERIES

Aug. 11 2021

 Presented research that was in the paper preparation stage. Talk title: Exploring the Link Between the Star Formation History and the Morphology of Galaxies in SDSS-IV MaNGA. Hosted by John Hopkins University, for conference details click here

Undergraduate Thesis Presentation

Toronto, Canada

PROJECT PRESENTER Apr. 12 2021

Presented research conducted during undergraduate thesis project. Talk title: Internal Kinematics of Galaxies in Relation to their Morphological Evolution Using MaNGA Survey. Presentation slides can be found here

Education

University of Toronto Toronto, Canada

HONS. BSc. IN ASTRONOMY AND PHYSICS

Sept. 2017 - Jun. 2021

- Math minor and Philosophy Minor
- Achieved cGPA of 3.60 (A-) across all astrophysics based courses, including 4.0 GPA in undergraduate thesis

Extracurricular

Languages

• Fluent in English and Spanish. Rudimentary ability to speak and read French. Currently learning Japanese, very basic ability to understand and read.

Technology

- · Take joy in playing around with various software applications/code on computers and other devices to optimize my experience
- · Enjoy understanding computer hardware and how it functions, built my own desktop computer